<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>


    <title>The NeuroBlog - Articles</title>
    <description>The official blog of the Graduate Students&#39; Association in Neuroscience at McGill University.</description>
    <link>
    https://blog.gsaneuro.com</link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>From 1D to 2D in the electrophysiology of the human retina - an interview with Mathieu Gauvin</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our new interview is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.ca/citations?hl=en&amp;amp;user=rb7UxjQAAAAJ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mathieu Gauvin&lt;/a&gt;, Ph.D. student supervised by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thechildren.com/departments-and-staff/staff/pierre-lachapelle-phd-director-visual-electrophysiology&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Pierre Lachapelle&lt;/a&gt; at the McGill Visual Electrophysiology Laboratory and Clinic. Mathieu works on the development of new methods for studying retinal function to better understand both normal and impaired visual processing. His findings (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26746684&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;published in the Journal of Vision&lt;/a&gt;) show how using some cutting-edge techniques when analyzing the human electroretinogram can uncover distinct markers of different types of retinal impairment. In a Q&amp;amp;A session with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gsaneuro.com/editors/&quot;&gt;Anastasia Glushko&lt;/a&gt;, Mathieu told us about his project and its clinical potential!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 15:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/05/26/mathieu-gauvin-ipn-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/05/26/mathieu-gauvin-ipn-interview/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Interview with Emily Coffey</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, we are starting to post interviews with our fellow graduate students in neuroscience at McGill! The first Q&amp;amp;A session we held was with Emily Coffey, Ph.D. student in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zlab.mcgill.ca/home.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the lab of Dr. Robert Zatorre&lt;/a&gt;. Earlier this year, Emily’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/ncomms/2016/160324/ncomms11070/full/ncomms11070.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;first-authored article based on her magnetoencephalography (MEG) investigation of the auditory frequency-following response&lt;/a&gt; (FFR) was published in Nature Communications. In their study, Emily and her colleagues showed that the FFR, a neurophysiological response to complex periodic sounds previously considered to be of purely subcortical origins, may in fact partially reflect contributions from the human auditory cortex. In other words, the use of MEG (instead of the electroencephalography, typically used for studying auditory brainstem responses) allowed the authors to see that the auditory cortex works together with the brainstem during sound periodicity analysis. NeuroBlog editor &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gsaneuro.com/editors/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Anastasia Glushko&lt;/a&gt; spoke to Emily about this study, and we hope you’ll enjoy reading what came out of this conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 15:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/04/27/emily-coffey-ipn-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/04/27/emily-coffey-ipn-interview/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The PhD Starter Kit</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Welcome back everybody from the Holidays and Happy New Year! Now that you are refreshed and ready to tackle your research, what better way to help you get started in the best way possible than a productivity post? Nothing, we should say! So here you go!&lt;br /&gt;
Our first post of the year is a guest post, written by Achintya Rao, a science communicator for CERN in Geneva on the CMS experiment and a second year PhD student. The post covers everything from general task management, to making presentations, and even coding. Enjoy!&lt;br /&gt;
To find out more about PhD life in general, and physics in particular, follow Achintya Rao on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RaoOfPhysics&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/+AchintyaRao/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/achintyarao&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-&lt;em&gt;Anastasia and Katrine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 18:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/the-phd-starter-kit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/the-phd-starter-kit/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to the NeuroBlog!</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Brace yourself, GSAN!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 18:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>