<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>


    <title>The NeuroBlog - Articles</title>
    <description>The official blog of the Graduate Students&#39; Association in Neuroscience at McGill University.</description>
    <link>
    https://blog.gsaneuro.com</link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>What can neuroscientists do against the stigma around mental illness? </title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Upon waking yesterday, I made my usual morning coffee and opened my laptop for a routine social media check. The Twitter feed was less regular: every second post featured Bell Let’s Talk day. In 2010, Bell launched a campaign to raise awareness of mental health issues and to prevent and reduce the stigma around them. For a day every year, Bell donates to mental health initiatives for every text message, call, or social media post with the #BellLetsTalk hashtag. Millions of people have joined the campaign over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2017/01/26/stigma-mental-illness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2017/01/26/stigma-mental-illness/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Do I deserve to be a PhD student?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Do you feel like everyone in your program or department is more intelligent than you? You may be experiencing impostor phenomenon. Anastasia Sares summed up the main characteristics of the phenomenon for the NeuroBlog and collected real data from a short questionnaire administered to IPN students. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 04:02:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2017/01/24/impostor-phenomenon/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2017/01/24/impostor-phenomenon/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>New Year&#39;s Resolutions</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Happy New Year neurograds! We asked about your resolutions for this year – from graduate research to life outside of the lab. We’ve combined them below, along with some of our own resolutions and tips. Here’s to a better year ahead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 06:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2017/01/06/new-years-resolutions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2017/01/06/new-years-resolutions/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Silencing pain with light: an interview with Ihab Daou</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The NeuroBlog is interviewing again! We’re excited to have the opportunity of speaking with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Ihab_Daou&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ihab Daou&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an accomplished PhD student in &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.mni.mcgill.ca/research/seguela/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Philippe Seguela’s lab&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at the Montreal Neurological Institute. In February 2016, Ihab first-authored an article describing a novel transgenic mouse model in which terminals of primary nociceptive fibers can be silenced using optogenetic techniques. In their study, Ihab and his colleagues were able to highlight the role of peripheral neuronal inputs in the onset and maintenance of pain hypersensitivity, and support the involvement of Na&lt;sub&gt;v&lt;/sub&gt;1.8&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; afferents in inflammatory and neuropathic pain. They have been able to “silence” fibers classically associated with pain in mice. They believe this non-invasive model will facilitate drug development for pain therapeutics. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gsaneuro.com/editors/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shannon Tansley&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; had the opportunity to speak with Ihab about his research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 15:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/08/22/ihab-daou-ipn-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/08/22/ihab-daou-ipn-interview/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Your brain on biased decision-making&amp;#58; an interview with Avinash Vaidya</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In our latest post, we introduce you to some very recent research conducted by Avinash Vaidya, who has just defended his Ph.D. thesis in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcgill.ca/decisionlab/home-page&quot;&gt;Dr. Lesley Fellows’&lt;/a&gt; lab at the Montreal Neurological Institute. Avinash worked with patients with frontal lobe lesions on topics related to decision-making. His &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/ncomms/2015/151214/ncomms10120/full/ncomms10120.html&quot;&gt;first-authored paper in Nature Communications&lt;/a&gt; investigates the neural circuitry underlying fixation-based value updating. In other words, Avinash investigated the fact that people are more likely to choose options that they have looked at (fixated) for a longer period of time, even if those options were perceived as less appealing initially.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Avinash and Dr. Fellows found that in individuals with damaged dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (PFC), this bias was significantly increased. This allowed them to conclude that the potential role of this brain area is in maintaining unattended values during decision-making. At the same time, other patient groups— those with damaged lateral and ventromedial prefrontal cortices—were even “better” than healthy adults in their decisions: their choices were more consistent with their initial ratings of the objects. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gsaneuro.com/editors/&quot;&gt;Anastasia Glushko&lt;/a&gt; interviewed Avinash for the NeuroBlog and wrote up the main points of their discussion – enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 15:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/07/06/avinash-vaidya-ipn-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/07/06/avinash-vaidya-ipn-interview/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>From 1D to 2D in the electrophysiology of the human retina&amp;#58; an interview with Mathieu Gauvin</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our new interview is with &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.ca/citations?hl=en&amp;amp;user=rb7UxjQAAAAJ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mathieu Gauvin&lt;/a&gt;, Ph.D. student supervised by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thechildren.com/departments-and-staff/staff/pierre-lachapelle-phd-director-visual-electrophysiology&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Pierre Lachapelle&lt;/a&gt; at the McGill Visual Electrophysiology Laboratory and Clinic. Mathieu works on the development of new methods for studying retinal function to better understand both normal and impaired visual processing. His findings (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26746684&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;published in the Journal of Vision&lt;/a&gt;) show how using some cutting-edge techniques when analyzing the human electroretinogram can uncover distinct markers of different types of retinal impairment. In a Q&amp;amp;A session with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gsaneuro.com/editors/&quot;&gt;Anastasia Glushko&lt;/a&gt;, Mathieu told us about his project and its clinical potential!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 15:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/05/26/mathieu-gauvin-ipn-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/05/26/mathieu-gauvin-ipn-interview/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Interview with Emily Coffey</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, we are starting to post interviews with our fellow graduate students in neuroscience at McGill! The first Q&amp;amp;A session we held was with Emily Coffey, Ph.D. student in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zlab.mcgill.ca/home.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the lab of Dr. Robert Zatorre&lt;/a&gt;. Earlier this year, Emily’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/ncomms/2016/160324/ncomms11070/full/ncomms11070.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;first-authored article based on her magnetoencephalography (MEG) investigation of the auditory frequency-following response&lt;/a&gt; (FFR) was published in Nature Communications. In their study, Emily and her colleagues showed that the FFR, a neurophysiological response to complex periodic sounds previously considered to be of purely subcortical origins, may in fact partially reflect contributions from the human auditory cortex. In other words, the use of MEG (instead of the electroencephalography, typically used for studying auditory brainstem responses) allowed the authors to see that the auditory cortex works together with the brainstem during sound periodicity analysis. NeuroBlog editor &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gsaneuro.com/editors/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Anastasia Glushko&lt;/a&gt; spoke to Emily about this study, and we hope you’ll enjoy reading what came out of this conversation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 15:01:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/04/27/emily-coffey-ipn-interview/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/04/27/emily-coffey-ipn-interview/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The PhD Starter Kit</title>
        
          <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Welcome back everybody from the Holidays and Happy New Year! Now that you are refreshed and ready to tackle your research, what better way to help you get started in the best way possible than a productivity post? Nothing, we should say! So here you go!&lt;br /&gt;
Our first post of the year is a guest post, written by Achintya Rao, a science communicator for CERN in Geneva on the CMS experiment and a second year PhD student. The post covers everything from general task management, to making presentations, and even coding. Enjoy!&lt;br /&gt;
To find out more about PhD life in general, and physics in particular, follow Achintya Rao on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RaoOfPhysics&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/+AchintyaRao/posts&quot;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/achintyarao&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;-&lt;em&gt;Anastasia and Katrine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 18:01:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/the-phd-starter-kit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/the-phd-starter-kit/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to the NeuroBlog!</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Brace yourself, GSAN!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 18:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>
        https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.gsaneuro.com/2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>