
---
layout: atom
title: nil
---

	<item>
	  <title>What can neuroscientists do against the stigma around mental illness? </title>
	  <link>//2017/01/26/stigma-mental-illness/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2017-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//2017/01/26/stigma-mental-illness/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Upon waking yesterday, I made my usual morning coffee and opened my laptop for a routine social media check. The Twitter feed was less regular: every second post featured Bell Let’s Talk day. In 2010, Bell launched a campaign to raise awareness of mental health issues and to prevent and reduce the stigma around them. For a day every year, Bell donates to mental health initiatives for every text message, call, or social media post with the #BellLetsTalk hashtag. Millions of people have joined the campaign over the years.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/assets/images/letstalk1.png" width="85%" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Source: <a href="https://twitter.com/JustinTrudeau/status/824255266137001984" target="_blank">https://twitter.com/JustinTrudeau/status/824255266137001984</a></em></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Logging in to the <a href="https://twitter.com/gsaneuro" target="_blank">GSAN Twitter account</a>, I immediately clicked on “Retweet” when I saw Justin Trudeau’s post about the campaign. Because obviously, I thought, who if not graduate students in neuroscience should be able to raise awareness about mental illness. And indeed, I saw quite a few posts / tweets / shares by McGill neuro-folks. It was great to witness the professional community being engaged and expressing the need for open conversation regarding mental health.</p>

<p>Bell Let’s Talk day is a yearly occurrence, but most of us (this is at least my impression) engage in raising awareness about mental health issues way more often. I came up with a short (and most probably incomplete) list of how we, neuroscience students / professionals, can contribute to the destigmatization of mental illness.</p>

<p><strong><em>Talk (neuro)science</em></strong>. It sometimes seems like we still don’t know much about the brain but it’s undeniable that we do know some things: from the very basic facts (e.g., depression is not a lifestyle choice) to the <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/gnxp/2012/06/heritability-of-behavioral-traits/" target="_blank">less widely-known</a> research findings. Are you an expert in a specific area of mental health research? Share your knowledge with friends (fun sciency facts over a beer –not much can beat that!), on your social media, or <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2014/apr/17/science-blog-wellcome-trust-writing-prize" target="_blank">blog about it</a>.</p>

<p><strong><em>Contact-based education.</em></strong> Sharing our own experiences with mental illness might be challenging but this is one other thing that works well in overcoming the stigma. I do struggle with mental health issues myself, and I can understand how difficult it might be to openly talk about them. My own experience so far, though, has mostly been positive. When I feel resourceful enough to share what my life is like during a period of depression or how going to a therapist is helping me cope, what I often hear back are words of support and understanding or expression of interest. Some responses are definitely less sensitive than others, but when I sense that I’m able to handle the typical “You should just go outside or do a workout” (I know these things might help, the issue is most of the time when I don’t feel well, I am not able to do them – oh the irony), I decide that sharing is worth it.</p>

<p>I believe that when a neuroscientist shares their struggles with mental health issues, it has an especially valuable effect: a combination of personal experience with professional expertise (although we must, of course, consider that both have their limits) is a powerful one. Sharing with people from academia may also be very important. First, being an academic is emotionally and intellectually demanding, and it’s essential for all of us to know that having mental health issues does not mean that a person cannot successfully handle their research projects and other academic responsibilities. Second, graduate students  <a href="http://www.universityaffairs.ca/opinion/speculative-diction/my-grief-lies-all-within-phd-students-depression-attrition/" target="_blank">often feel overwhelmed and isolated</a>, and sharing with your peers might help both sides in not feeling alone in this and could encourage conversation about coping mechanisms, including the opportunities of getting help.</p>

<p><strong>Reach out</strong>. At McGill and in Montreal, we have plenty of opportunities to get involved in more organized community outreach and volunteer programs. Here are some of them:<br />
1.	Talk about brain science to elementary and high school students in and around Montreal with <a href="https://www.mcgill.ca/ipn/brainreach" target="_blank">BrainReach</a><br />
2.	Volunteer at the  <a href="http://brainawarenessmontreal.com/baw-volunteers/" target="_blank">Brain Awareness Week in Montreal</a><br />
3.	Take part in the <a href="http://studentsinmind.strikingly.com/" target="_blank">Students in Mind Mental Health conference</a><br />
4.	Join the  <a href="http://www.mcgill.ca/peerprograms/students-seeking-peer-support" target="_blank">Peer Support network</a><br />
5. <a href="https://mentalhealthweek.cmha.ca/files/2016/04/PublicToolkit.pdf" target="_blank">Host a fundraiser</a> during the <a href="http://mentalhealthweek.cmha.ca/participate/host-fundraising-event/" target="_blank">Canadian Mental Health Association’s</a> Mental Health Week<br />
6.	Join one of the  <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pgssequity/?fref=ts" target="_blank">PGSS</a> or <a href="https://www.mcgill.ca/senate/committeesofsenate/standingcommittees/joint-board-senate-committee-equity" target="_blank">McGill</a> committees that work on preventing stigmatization of mental illness</p>

<p>So, here are a couple of ideas to keep ourselves busy until the next mental health awareness campaign pops up on our social media. If you think I should add anything else to my mini-list or have any other comments,  <a href="mailto:NeuroBlog.GSAN@gmail.com" target="_blank">let me know</a>!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Do I deserve to be a PhD student?</title>
	  <link>//2017/01/24/impostor-phenomenon/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2017-01-24T04:02:00-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//2017/01/24/impostor-phenomenon/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>

  <p>Do you feel like everyone in your program or department is more intelligent than you? You may be experiencing impostor phenomenon. Anastasia Sares summed up the main characteristics of the phenomenon for the NeuroBlog and collected real data from a short questionnaire administered to IPN students. Enjoy!</p>

</blockquote>

<p>In the 1970s, Pauline Clance and Suzanne Imes identified a set of feelings in their university students and graduates known as “The impostor phenomenon”. People who experience impostor phenomenon (IP)… maintain a strong belief that they are not intelligent; in fact they are convinced that they have fooled anyone who thinks otherwise.” (Clance &amp; Imes, 1978).</p>

<p>Now, I’m not sure if I’m marked by a complete inability to internalize my successes, but being in a doctoral program does challenge me to the point where, at times, I’m not sure I belong. It’s a common story. Many of us have grown up building our identity around our competence and intelligence. This is what led us to graduate school in the first place. But when we got here, we found that we were surrounded by people just as competent and intelligent as us— some even more so. We began to doubt. To minimize our earlier accomplishments. To be afraid to ask questions that might show our ignorance.</p>

<p>A 2011 Scientific American <a href="http://www.nature.com/scientificamericanmind/journal/v22/n1/full/scientificamericanmind0311-32.html" target="_blank">article</a> by Birgit Spinath highlighted the fact that IP may be related to attributional style (e.g. Peterson et al., 1982). In other words, people with IP may perceive success to be due to external factors (like over-preparation) and situations (nice reviewers, easy questions). Failure, on the other hand, is viewed as internal, stable, and global. The same vocabulary is used to talk about depression, and indeed there seems to be a link between depression and IP.</p>

<p>Spinath’s article says it’s unclear whether IP affects women disproportionately, as depression does; though early articles from Clance herself focused specifically on women, and some have suggested that female dropout in higher education is partially due to impostor phenomenon.</p>

<p>Dr. Clance created a <a href="http://paulineroseclance.com/pdf/IPscoringtest.pdf" target="_blank">short questionnaire</a> for people who might be experiencing impostor phenomenon (note that this is not a diagnostic tool; it’s only for the purposes of self-help). We decided to take this questionnaire to IPN members and see how they measured up. A survey of 30 students (15 female, 15 male) revealed a shocking average score of 71 +/- 13. This is well into the range for impostor phenomenon, according to Clance, although only scores above 80 correspond to “intense” IP experiences. No one in our sample scored below 40, which is Clance’s cutoff between no IP and mild IP feelings.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/assets/images/impostor1.png" width="85%" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Score Distribution</em></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Scores tended to decrease with number of years in the IPN, indicating perhaps that confidence increases with experience in a graduate setting. Males also had a lower average score than females. However, neither of these trends was significant with all participants pooled together (rs &lt; -0.233; ps &gt; 0.143). A different story emerged when we split the data by gender: we found that males’ scores did decrease significantly over time (r = -0.555; p = 0.0317), whereas females’ scores did not (r = 0.0019; p = 0.995).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/assets/images/impostor2.png" width="85%" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Score by year in IPN</em></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Of course, we need to be cautious with this sample, as it likely consisted of the most active and responsive IPN members, who may have a different profile than other graduate students. Also, many people who filled the questionnaire had already heard of impostor phenomenon before, either from someone else in academia or on the internet.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="/assets/images/impostor3.png" width="85%" /></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>1) Have you heard about impostor phenomenon? 2) Where did you hear about it?</em></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<hr />

<p>Knowing about impostor phenomenon is all well and good, but what do you do when you find yourself (like I did) sitting up at midnight wondering whether it would be socially acceptable for you to drop out of your degree? How does one deal with impostor feelings? Here are a few ways to get started:</p>

<ol>
  <li><em>Realize that it’s not just you</em>. You are not the first person to feel like this. That alone can be immensely comforting. In fact, you know the people you compare yourself to, wishing you could be smart, organized, or confident like them? Some of them probably feel like impostors too.</li>
  <li><em>Review your accomplishments</em>. Go back to your CV, and instead of looking at what’s lacking, look at what’s there. See how many milestones you’ve crossed and how far you’ve come. Compare yourself to yourself.</li>
  <li><em>Realize that it’s not all bad</em>. “Good” and “bad” personality traits are often two sides of the same coin. See Zachary Lippman’s short post: An ego can be a <a href="http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/articles/10.1038/nj7220-418c" target="_blank">dangerous monster</a>.</li>
  <li><em>Reach out</em>. McGill’s <a href="https://www.mcgill.ca/counselling/" target="_blank">counseling service</a> is in place to help you sort through these kind of thoughts, as are your peers. Don’t go through this alone.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h4 id="references">References:</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>Clance, P.R., &amp; Imes, S. A. (1978).<br />
The impostor phenomenon in high achieving women: Dynamics and therapeutic intervention.<br />
<em>Psychotherapy: Theory, Research, and Practice</em>, 15(3), 241-247.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Spinath, B. (2011).<br />
Great Pretenders.<br />
<em>Scientific American Mind</em>, 22(1), 32–37. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1525/si.1997.20.3.315" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1525/si.1997.20.3.315</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Peterson, C., Semmel, A., von Baeyer, C., Abramson, L., Metalsky, G., &amp; Seligman, M. (1982).<br />
The Attributional Style Questionnaire.<br />
<em>Cognitive Therapy and Research</em>, 6(3), 287–300.</p>
</blockquote>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

