
---
layout: atom
title: nil
---

	<item>
	  <title>Welcome to the NeuroBlog!</title>
	  <link>//2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2016-01-20T18:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Brace yourself, GSAN!</p>

<p>Together with the real winter (finally!), the brand new Neuroblog is on its way! We want to introduce to you a special project for the GSAN blog. Alongside our own posts about pretty much anything that could be interesting for a graduate neuroscience student at McGill, we will from now on have an interview section! Exciting, eh?… Well, let us tell you all about it!</p>

<p><strong>What kind of interviews?</strong></p>

<p>The idea is to post interviews with graduate neuroscience students at McGill who have recently published their research in a peer-reviewed journal. Questions will be about the student’s project, and the answers are supposed to be communicated in a language and form that’s accessible to people with basic knowledge in neuroscience.</p>

<p><strong>Why interviews?</strong></p>

<p>There are so many cool things about interviews! Interviews are the “direct speech” of one of your colleagues, addressing the diverse GSAN community. They are vivid stories about real projects and individual research experiences of neuroscience students at McGill. Such a format makes it simple to catch up with what is going on in the McGill’s neuroscience community. We will also promote the interviews on the IPN social media pages, which will help prospective students get an idea about graduate life at McGill, and will also give some publicity to the students who’ve been interviewed!</p>

<p><strong>How do the interviews go?</strong><br />
1. The Neuroblog coordinators are constantly tracking the publications coming from GSAN members.<br />
2. We then select those papers that seem most interesting for the GSAN community (the decision is made by several GSAN committee members).<br />
3. The coordinators contact the potential interviewees.<br />
4. If the interviewee is interesting in participating, the coordinators study the relevant literature and prepare a list of questions about the interviewee’s research project. The questions are then sent to the interviewee via e-mail.<br />
5. After the prospective interviewee sends back written answers to the questions, there might be a couple of short follow-up questions from the interviewers (again, coordinated through e-mail).<br />
6. That’s it! When we get the last responses, we post the interview along with some basic information about the interviewee on the GSAN Blog.</p>

<p>Want to tell the world about the research you’ve recently published?</p>

<p>Write us an e-mail!</p>

<p><code>NeuroBlog.GSAN [at] gmail [dot] com</code></p>

<p><em>Anastasia and Katrine</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

