
---
layout: atom
title: nil
---

	<item>
	  <title>New Year's Resolutions</title>
	  <link>//2017/01/06/new-years-resolutions/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2017-01-06T06:01:00-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//2017/01/06/new-years-resolutions/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>

  <p>Happy New Year neurograds! We asked about your resolutions for this year – from graduate research to life outside of the lab. We’ve combined them below, along with some of our own resolutions and tips. Here’s to a better year ahead!</p>

</blockquote>

<h3 id="engage">Engage</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Try something new</strong>: a new technique in lab, a planning system, a genre of books, a sport, a skill, or a new way to relax.</li>
  <li><strong>Take advantage of common interests in the grad student community</strong>: join a group for sports, music, art, or crafts (knitting group!); contribute to journal clubs; attend GSAN events; play board games; code together in Hackspace; learn a new language in GSAN language classes; learn together and seek insight from others outside the lab.</li>
  <li><strong>Find new inspiration</strong>: attend special lectures within and outside of IPN; present at small conferences; ask more questions at poster sessions and talks; reach out to the community for feedback; work up the courage to talk to that researcher whose work you admire; step outside of your focus sometimes for perspective.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="reflect">Reflect</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Manage time</strong>: set daily, weekly, and monthly actionable goals; gradually adjust your sleep schedule; take more small breaks; write a little every day; budget more realistic amounts of time for studying or reading; change up your tasks when you lose focus; actively allot time in the week for cooking, cleaning, exercise, and rest; don’t let perfect be the enemy of the good. (Tip: Go about your week as normal and write down how you spend your time. At the end of the week, assess how much time you typically spend on your commute, your meals, checking your email, writing, studying, lab work, chores, etc. Reflect on your priorities and use this information to set a realistic schedule, or adjust how much time you spend on certain tasks.)</li>
  <li><strong>Make time</strong>: make your art again; make music; see a show; craft; play in the snow; hike up Mount Royal; call your family; play a game; sleep; make comfort food; dance; exercise; explore somewhere new; go to a café or museum alone; set reminders to connect with friends; allow yourself to disconnect from work for part of the day (set do not disturb on your phone/email); set stopping points for work to better take advantage of time off; take time to think.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="connect">Connect</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Listen</strong>: be a new student buddy; attend a PGSS meeting; try or volunteer for the peer support network; talk to someone new after class or at an event; try a new podcast or audiobook as a group; attend student talks; connect with international students; go to a different club meeting or event; meet with students that work in other institutes; learn about research throughout Montreal.</li>
  <li><strong>Share</strong>: write about your work for a lay audience; discuss your interests in a public platform; make a video, graphic, or multimedia work about your research; give more practice talks to your labmates and other students; contribute to a scientific outreach program (Brain Reach, Let’s Talk Science); participate in 3 Minute Thesis; contribute to the Neuroblog!</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>

  <p>This year, we want to hear more about your research, your interests, and your life as a graduate student at McGill. Share your news with us, your passions, your challenges, and what you’d like to see more of here on the blog. Improve your writing by contributing, or simply share some of your photos from lab, conferences, or events. We look forward to sharing this next year with you! Cheers to a happy holiday season and an exciting new year.</p>

</blockquote>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Welcome to the NeuroBlog!</title>
	  <link>//2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2016-01-20T18:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//2016/01/20/welcome-to-neuroblog/</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Brace yourself, GSAN!</p>

<p>Together with the real winter (finally!), the brand new Neuroblog is on its way! We want to introduce to you a special project for the GSAN blog. Alongside our own posts about pretty much anything that could be interesting for a graduate neuroscience student at McGill, we will from now on have an interview section! Exciting, eh?… Well, let us tell you all about it!</p>

<p><strong>What kind of interviews?</strong></p>

<p>The idea is to post interviews with graduate neuroscience students at McGill who have recently published their research in a peer-reviewed journal. Questions will be about the student’s project, and the answers are supposed to be communicated in a language and form that’s accessible to people with basic knowledge in neuroscience.</p>

<p><strong>Why interviews?</strong></p>

<p>There are so many cool things about interviews! Interviews are the “direct speech” of one of your colleagues, addressing the diverse GSAN community. They are vivid stories about real projects and individual research experiences of neuroscience students at McGill. Such a format makes it simple to catch up with what is going on in the McGill’s neuroscience community. We will also promote the interviews on the IPN social media pages, which will help prospective students get an idea about graduate life at McGill, and will also give some publicity to the students who’ve been interviewed!</p>

<p><strong>How do the interviews go?</strong><br />
1. The Neuroblog coordinators are constantly tracking the publications coming from GSAN members.<br />
2. We then select those papers that seem most interesting for the GSAN community (the decision is made by several GSAN committee members).<br />
3. The coordinators contact the potential interviewees.<br />
4. If the interviewee is interesting in participating, the coordinators study the relevant literature and prepare a list of questions about the interviewee’s research project. The questions are then sent to the interviewee via e-mail.<br />
5. After the prospective interviewee sends back written answers to the questions, there might be a couple of short follow-up questions from the interviewers (again, coordinated through e-mail).<br />
6. That’s it! When we get the last responses, we post the interview along with some basic information about the interviewee on the GSAN Blog.</p>

<p>Want to tell the world about the research you’ve recently published?</p>

<p>Write us an e-mail!</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">NeuroBlog.GSAN [at] gmail [dot] com</code></p>

<p><em>Anastasia and Katrine</em></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

